<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confession of faith, published on special occasion wherein is contained the substance of the most material principels of the Gospel and Christian faith, in contradistinction to the errors and heresies by some held and maintained, in opposition thereunto : whereunto is annexed a postscript, with brief animadversions on some things contained in a confession of faith, lately published in the name of the elders and brethren of many congregations in London and the countrey / written by Thomas Collier.</title>
            <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12706554</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12706554</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66029</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66029)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1524:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confession of faith, published on special occasion wherein is contained the substance of the most material principels of the Gospel and Christian faith, in contradistinction to the errors and heresies by some held and maintained, in opposition thereunto : whereunto is annexed a postscript, with brief animadversions on some things contained in a confession of faith, lately published in the name of the elders and brethren of many congregations in London and the countrey / written by Thomas Collier.</title>
                  <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Creeds.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
               <term>Election (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66029:1"/>
            <p>A CONFESSION OF FAITH, <hi>Publiſhed on ſpecial occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is contained the Subſtance of the moſt material Principles of the Goſpel, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, in contradiſtinction to the Errors and Hereſies by ſome held and maintained, in oppoſition thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed,</hi> A POSTSCRIPT, with brief Animadverſions on ſome things, contained in a <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> lately publiſhed in the name of the Elders and Brethren of many Congregations in <hi>London</hi> and the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>THOMAS COLLIER.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 8. 20.</bibl>
            <q>To the Law and to the Teſtimony: if they ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</q>
            <bibl>Tim. 3. 8, 9.</bibl>
            <q>
               <hi>Now as</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>withſtood</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth: Men of corrupt minds, reprobate</hi> (or of no judgment) <hi>concerning the faith. But they ſhall proceed no further: for their folly ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt unto all men, as theirs alſo was.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal Exchange, 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66029:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66029:2"/>
            <head>A Confeſsion of Faith.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Concerning God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Believe that there is one only true God, the Great Almighty one, who hath his Being in and of himſelf, and hath given Being unto all things, the great Creator and Preſerver of all things, <hi>Deut. 6. 4. Iſa. 4. 21. 2 Cor. 8. 6. Gen. 1. 1. Act.</hi> 17. 24 to 28. That he is an Infinite Spirit, moſt Holy, Wiſe, Juſt, Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Faithful, <hi>Joh. 4. 24. 1 Sam. 2. 2. Iſa. 6. 3. Pſal. 147. 5. Iſa. 40. 28. Deut. 32. 4. Zeph. 3. 5. Exod. 34. 6. Mic. 7. 8. Tit. 3. 4. Deut. 7 9. Tit.</hi> 1. 2. Eternal and Omnipreſent in all Places, <hi>Deut. 33. 27. Iſa. 57. 15. Pſal.</hi> 139. 7 to 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet I do believe according to his Word, that his moſt glorious Habitation, Dwelling-place, and Throne is in Heaven, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 15. and 66. 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I do believe that God made Man upright, in his own Image, and that by Sin he fell from that Eſtate, into an Eſtate of Sin and Death, <hi>Eccl. 7. 29. Gen.</hi> 1. 27. and 3. 17, 18, 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66029:3"/>4. I do believe (as the great foundation-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Truth and of Faith,) that God loved the World in the gift of his Son, <hi>Joh. 3. 16. 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 14. which was the only means and way deſigned of God, for the recovery of Man out of his faln Eſtate, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. and 22. 18. <hi>Act. 4. 12. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 21, 22.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As I do believe that God is, ſo do I believe <hi>that he is a Rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him,</hi> this being one ſpecial Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Concerning Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That he is the Son of God, and the Son of Man, truly God and Man, <hi>made of the Seed of</hi> David <hi>according to the Fleſh,</hi> Rom. 1. 3, 4. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Holy Ghoſt, in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> according to the Scriptures, <hi>Iſa. 17. 14. Jer. 31. 22. Mat.</hi> 1. 22, 23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he was begotten, known, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized in his whole Perſon by the Father, before Time, both God and Man, as he was made Fleſh, and dwelt among us in Time, (yet his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not in Being, till made Fleſh of the Seed of <hi>David,) Heb. 1. 6. Col.</hi> 1. 15. and therefore he is ſaid <hi>to come out from God, and down from Heaven,</hi> Joh. 3. 13. and 6. 51, 62. and 16. 28, 30. and 17. 8. 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 47. Eph.</hi> 4. 9 11. and that it was he by whom <hi>all things were made,</hi> Joh. 1. 1, 2, 3, 10. and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66029:3"/> that the Father, Son, and Spirit, are in nature and eſſence one, yet in office and relative proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and operations are three, and yet an unity in nature and concent in Will and Work, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 17, 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That after he had finiſhed the Work he had to do in the World, by which he declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the Son, and ſent of God, the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> promiſed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 36. and 10. 25. and 17. 4. and 20 30, 31. according to the great love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the end for which he ſent him into the World, he gave himſelf a Sin and Peace-offering to God the Father, for the ſins of the World, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 29. and 6. 51. 1 <hi>Tim. 2. 6. Heb. 1. 1. 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 2. and as an effect thereof, hath ſent forth the Goſpel of his Grace, by commiſſion to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the World, that whoever do believe and obey him therein, may have the ſaving Benefits thereof, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15, 16. and that the Father and the Son in this wonderful tranſaction, had real love to the World therein, and hated none. That when God is ſaid to hate any, it is becauſe of Sin, and not as his Creatures, that in this ſenſe he is good to all, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 9. and ſeeks to ſave them from their ſins, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 16, 17, 18, 19. and that Jeſus Chriſt crucified is the only Foundation of Chriſtian Faith, and not in the divine Nature only, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 11. and 2. 2.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons why I believe this general love of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66029:4"/> God and Chriſt to the World, in this wonderful Goſpel-undertaking, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Scripture ſaith it, and if I ſhould not ſo believe, I ſhould (as many others do) make God and Chriſt Lyars, which is the great and damning ſin, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 10. with <hi>Mark 16. 15, 16. But he that believeth the teſtimony that God hath given of his Son, hath ſet to his Seal that God is true,</hi> Joh. 3. 33.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the denial hereof rooteth up the foundation of Goſpel-preaching, there being three things that God hath ſet in unity in this matter, that Man may not put aſunder, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nulling the whole deſign of God in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> of Goſpel-preaching, of Life to the World, on the terms thereof.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The general love of God to the World in the gift of his Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And ſutable to this general Love of God to the World, is Chriſt giving himſelf a Sacrifice for the ſins of the World, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 51. The Sacrifice muſt be as large as the Fathers love, elſe it anſwers not his Will and End in giving his Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 7.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Sutable to this general Love, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sacrifice, is the general Commiſſion for publiſhing thereof to the World, that ſo they might underſtand and believe this Love, and be ſaved, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15, 16. Theſe three are as large one as the other, and ſtand in unity: take away
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66029:4"/> the general Love of the Father, and the general Sacrifice of the Son, and the general Commiſſion ceaſeth, it being grounded on the two former; ſo that deny the two firſt, and it ends Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As an Effect, becauſe the denial hereof rooteth up the Foundation of Goſpel-Faith; for if the Foundation of Goſpel-preaching be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then Goſpel-Faith muſt ceaſe, it being no part of the Doctrine of the Goſpel, that Chriſt was a Sacrifice only for a few, it can be no part of Goſpel-Faith ſo to believe: if it were, the Doctrine of the Goſpel muſt give a very <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſound, and then who could prepare himſelf to the Battel?</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 8. But it not being ſo, an open way is made, and a ſure foundation is laid in the Goſpel, to build our Faith upon, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 16. And as this is the Doctrine, ſo this is the Faith of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 3, 11. So we preach, and ſo ye believed,</hi> i. e. <hi>that Chriſt died for our ſins,</hi> the firſt Doctrine that is to be preached to ſinners, and ſo the firſt that is to be believed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the denial hereof leaves all that miſcarry through unbelief to periſh for want of a Saviour, and not through their own unbelief and diſobedience to the Goſpel, as the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, which maketh God a Lyar, <hi>Joh. 3. 18. Heb. 3. 8. Jude</hi> v. 5. For if any ſuch were, for whom Chriſt died not, if ſuch ſhould believe, they could not be ſaved, there being no Salvation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66029:5"/> but by this one Sacrifice: If ſuch ſhould believe, they muſt believe a Lye, and ſo could not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; nay, but they muſt damned for believing a Lye, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 11, 12. And it would be their vertue to believe that Chriſt died not for them, if it were true; becauſe it is a vertue to believe a Truth, and a vice to believe a Lye. So that by this Doctrine, all that periſh do periſh for want of a Saviour, and not through diſobedience: but <hi>let God be true, and all Men lyars</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe the ſpecial Grace of Life promiſed in the Goſpel is founded in the general Grace of God in Chriſt to the World; ſo that if there be no ſuch general Grace of God in the Goſpel truly propounded to the World, then there is no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ground to believe any Goſpel-Grace to Men at all, <hi>Joh. 3. 16, 17. Mar.</hi> 16. 15, 16. Deny this, and Goſpel-Grace is ended and over, the ſpecial Grace of Reconciliation and Salvation being ſtated in Scripture as ariſing out from, or as an effect of general Grace, <hi>Rom. 5. 8 9, 10, 11. 2 Cor. 5. 9, 20. Col.</hi> 1. 20, 21. So that, they that will have no ſuch general Grace, as a ſure foundation to encourage Sinners to believe and obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel that they may be ſaved, can aſſure no ſpecial Grace and Salvation to any: ſo that in denying the general Grace of God in the Goſpel to Men, is in effect (though not intentionally) a real denying of all Grace, and ſo a denying of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66029:5"/> own Salvation, in denying the foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Becauſe to deny the general Love of God to the World, and the general Sacrifice and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt for the World, doth in effect really deny the Reſurrection of all, <hi>the Reſtitution of all things, the eternal Judgment,</hi> the World to come, and the glory of Chriſt's Kingdom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; all which depend upon this one Sacrifice given <hi>for the life of the World,</hi> Joh. 6. 51. 1 <hi>Cor. 15 21, 22. Act.</hi> 4. 2. &amp; 17. 31. ſo that the denial of Chriſt a Sacrifice for the ſins of the World, not only maketh God and Chriſt Lyars, endeth all Goſpel-preaching and Goſpel-Faith, leaving People to periſh for want of a Saviour, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ends the Reſurrection, Judgment, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt in the World to come; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a Principle that in it ſelf is deeply hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, meet to be huſh'd out of all Chriſtian ſociety. Yet I ſhall not call thoſe Hereticks who do ſo hold, becauſe I hope they do it ignorantly, in unbelief, as ſometime I my ſelf did, though it's now my grief that I ſhould be ignorant of ſo great a Truth, and can ſay (through Grace) that I have had ſome inſpection hereinto, for above twenty Years.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Becauſe the denial of this great Truth of the general Grace of God to Men in the Goſpel, is not only unſcriptural and contrary to it, but likewiſe irrational; and for Men to believe irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66029:6"/> things againſt Scripture-light, ſeems moſt ſtrange.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's not only irreligious (being contrary to the Scripture) but irrational, to believe that God ſhould in this his wonderful. Goſpel-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of Love and Grace to Men, deſign and determine Salvation to ſo few, and the Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World without all hope and means of help, is irrational to imagine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's irrational as well as irreligious, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Scripture ſo in this matter, as tends to render it obnoxious, ridiculous, and falſe, in ſaying, <hi>That God ſo loved the World</hi> in the gift of his Son, <hi>that whoſoever do believe in him, ſhall not periſh;</hi> and that the Goſpel <hi>is the good will of God to Men,</hi> and that Chriſt gave himſelf <hi>for the Life of the World,</hi> and yet intended no ſuch thing, but the Damnation of the World: for if Chriſt had not died, and been raiſed again, there had been no ſuch thing as Salvation or Damnation to any, becauſe there had been no Reſurrection, and ſo no Judgment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21, 22. and 17. 18, 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 31. So that this contradicting notion tends really to render thoſe Scriptures to ſound (if what they ſay were true) that God ſo hated the World that he ſent his Son to damn the World, and that God ſent his Son to die for the World, for no other end but to raiſe them up that they might be damned: which is both irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and irrational to imagine.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66029:6"/>3. It's irrational for us to believe (contrary to the Scripture) that God ſhould have ſo little reſpect to the glory of his own Name in ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful an undertaking, it being more glorious to the Name of God, for his Son to die for a World, to reſtore a World, to lay a foundation of Faith and Salvation for all ſuch as fall in with, and glorify him in his wonderful Grace to Men, and irrational to narrow and limit it to ſo few, ſo exceeding contrary to the Scripture, and deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the glory of ſo wonderful an Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's irrational (as well as irreligious) to believe that God in his Word ſhould complement with the World, as if he loved them, to offer them Grace, on gracious, holy, and honourable terms, to call and invite them with promiſes of acceptance, as if he intended good will unto them, and will damn them the deeper in Hell for their diſobedience (as themſelves affirm,) and yet never intended any Grace to them, nor could intend it, if Chriſt died not for them. As if God dealt with poor periſhing Sinners, as <hi>Joab</hi> dealt with <hi>Amaſa,</hi> 2 Sam. 2. 9, 10. and as <hi>Judas</hi> dealt with Chriſt, to offer them a kiſs of love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10, 11, 12. deſignedly to damn them the deeper in Hell, is both irreligious and irrational to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
               <p>That which is uſually objected in this matter, is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 16. to 22. and 11. 7. <hi>That God hath</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66029:7"/> 
                  <hi>from his own will reprobated ſome, and they cannot be ſaved, but muſt periſh: That Chriſt died not for them, nor was any good will in the Goſpel intended to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To this I ſay, That we may not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Decrees of God, ſo as may contradict his revealed Will and Law of Grace to Men, which calleth upon all, and promiſeth life to all that do believe and obey him therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it's both irreligious and irrational ſo to underſtand one or two Scriptures, as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the whole Word of God that ſpeaks of the ſame matter, where God ſaith, not only that he loved the World in the gift of his Son, and that he <hi>taſted death for every one,</hi> and calleth and inviteth all to accept the Grace, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 17. But alſo ſaith, <hi>that he hath no pleaſure in the death of him that dieth, and why will ye die?</hi> And anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to it, that he <hi>hath no pleaſure in the death of the Wicked, but that they would turn and live,</hi> Ezek. 18, 31, 32. and 33. 11. and that Men by ſin deſtroy themſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 9. So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4. he <hi>would have all Men to be ſaved,</hi> &amp;c. And it muſt needs be both irreligious and irrational ſo to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <hi>Rom. 9.</hi> as to contradict and give the lye to all theſe Scriptures, and many more.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We may ſo underſtand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. as is both Religious, God-like, and Rational, ſo as will comport with the whole Scripture and Analogy of Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> That when Men have hardned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66029:7"/> themſelves againſt the Mercy and means of good by God offered them for their ſpiritual and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal welfare, which was the preſent caſe relative to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the ſame of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> likewiſe brought as an inſtance, and of which the believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gentiles</hi> were (and are) in danger, if they ſo ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 20, 21. and in this caſe God is at liberty to exerciſe Juſtice and Mercy as he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without any derogation to his Goſpel-Law of Grace.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>If God willeth the good of all, is he not able to effect it? doth he will what he cannot effect?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This with ſome is much pleaded, though as wide from truth as weak: We are to diſtinguiſh between his Effecting and his Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Will, his revealed and requiring Will being his abſolute Will to us, and contrary to which we may not ſuppoſe any ſecret Will in God; and it's enough for us to know his abſolute revealed Will, with ſufficiency of means and helps for performance thereof, on neglect of which the Damnation will ariſe.</p>
               <p>The abſolute revealed Will of God to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of old was, that they ſhould keep his Law, and yet they tranſgreſſed it: and dare any ſay, it was not his real Will ſo to have it, but that he had a ſecret Will contrary thereunto? Let ſuch read and ponder <hi>Pſal. 81. 13. Iſa.</hi> 48. 18. and the ſame in the Goſpel, <hi>Luk. 13. 34.</hi> and 19. 41, 42. where they may find the Lord pitying them for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66029:8"/> their miſcarriage in this matter; unleſs they will judge him as right at the Art of diſſimulation as ſome Men are, which is Blaſphemy againſt him ſo to imagine.</p>
               <p>God hath not engaged himſelf to effect in us what he requireth of us, unleſs we (by his Grace) cloſe in with his Will made known unto us. God's Grace and our Duties muſt unite, if the work be done, <hi>Rom. 1. 16. Iſa. 64. 5. 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 19. ſo that it's moſt apparent that Men may, and too often do tranſgreſs the abſolute Will of God to their own deſtruction, <hi>Hoſ. 13. 9. Pſal.</hi> 81. 11, 12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I do believe that when our Lord Jeſus <hi>had by himſelf purged our ſins, he aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſate on the right hand of the Majeſty on high,</hi> Mar. 16. 19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 3. and is there in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Mediatory-office between God and Men, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. and that he is the alone King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his Church; King to rule, Prieſt to atone, and Prophet to teach; and that there is no other ſo, in things of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Goſpel concern.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That he ſhall come again from thence, at the time appointed, and ſhall raiſe the dead, and <hi>judge both the quick and dead at his appearing and Kingdom,</hi> Joh. 28. 29. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. and that then all that have been under the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſhall receive their eternal Judgment either of life or death, according to the promiſes and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66029:8"/> threats thereof in the Goſpel, <hi>Mar. 16. 15, 16. Joh.</hi> 3. 19. and 5. 28, 29. and that at (and after) his appearing, ſhall be the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 21. the new and reſtored World, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 13. Rev.</hi> 21. 1, 5. in and over which with his Saints, ſhall be his eternal Kingdom and Glory, <hi>Iſa. 9. 7. Dan. 7. 14, 17. Mar.</hi> 10. 30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Of the Scriptures.</head>
               <p>3. I do believe that the Holy Scriptures, the Old and New Teſtament, is the Word and Will of God, and eſpecially the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel contained therein, is the alone Ground and Rule both of Faith and Practice, <hi>Iſa. 8. 20. 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 15, 16, 17. For this more full, ſee my <hi>B. d. Chap. 2.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Of the way in which we may obtain the Life promiſed in the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>4. That Faith in (Repentance) and obedience to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, are the terms of our Intereſt in the juſtification and life therein promiſed, and that ſo abſolutely the condition thereof, as that without which none that are capable Subjects can obtain it, <hi>Mar. 16. 15, 16. Heb. 5. 9. Rev.</hi> 22. 14. yet not the meritorious or deſerving cauſe thereof, that being alone in Chriſt Jeſus, as the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66029:9"/> only atoning Sacrifice for ſin, <hi>Col. 1. 20. Eph.</hi> 5. 2. and that whoever do believe in, love, and obey the Lord in the Goſpel, ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Mar. 16. 15, 16. Act. 16. 31. Heb.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons why I believe, that not only Faith but Goſpel-obedience and works are the terms of our Intereſt in Juſtification and Life, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Doctrine of the Goſpel ſo ſtates it, not only in the Scriptures before mentioned, but likewiſe in many others, as <hi>Mat. 7. 18, 19, 20. Rom. 2. 8, 9, 10. Gal. 5. 6. Jam.</hi> 2, 14, 17, 20. to 26. 1 <hi>Joh. 2. 17. But he that doth the will of God, obideth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith without works, as it is ſcriptureleſs, and ſo falſe; ſo it is a graceleſs, licentious and vain Doctrine, that will not, cannot ſave, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 14, 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And that both the Faith and Works muſt be ſuch as the Goſpel requireth, and not what Men pleaſe; or elſe the Lord will ſay at that day, <hi>who required theſe things at your hands?</hi> And among all the vertues and duties required in the Goſpel as concomitants with Faith, Love to God and Men are the chief, <hi>Mat. 22. 37, 39. Rom. 13. 8. Jam. 2, 8. Eph. 6. 24. 1 Cor.</hi> 16 22. becauſe, where this is in truth, it carrieth on to the right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all other Duties both to God and Men: and where this is wanting, there can be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66029:9"/> no Religion in Truth, or acceptable with God: Faith without Love to God, and Love and Mercy to Men, will never juſtifie nor ſave, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 1, 2. Jam.</hi> 1. 27. and 2. 14. and the reaſon is, becauſe the Goſpel is a Miniſtration wholly of Love and Mercy, and the Love and Mercy of God in the Goſpel is manifeſt, eſpecially in giving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; and this he expects ſhould be effected by the Power thereof in all his People. And it's to be feared, that the great failing among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in this matter (much ariſing from the Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith without Works) will occaſion many to part with Chriſt at the laſt day with Sorrow, as the young Man did in the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 22. becauſe there will then <hi>be Judgment without Mercy, to them that have ſhewed no Mercy,</hi> James 2. 12. Read and ponder <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 32, to 35. and I do believe, that whatever is ſtated in the Goſpel as the terms on which Grace and Life is promiſed, is abſolutely neceſſary thereunto, without which we cannot rightly claim the Promiſe, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 3, to 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 7, to 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Of the Power and Will of Man.</head>
               <p>I do believe that all Men have a power and liberty of Will, with the means and helps that God affords (eſpecially under the Goſpel,) to refuſe the Evil, and to chuſe the Good, ſo far as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66029:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66029:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66029:11"/> will render them inexcuſable in the Judgment, who refuſe his Counſel, and chooſe to follow their own Wills and Luſts, <hi>Joſh. 24. 15, 22. Luk. 10. 42. Phil. 2. 12, 13, 14 15. Mat. 11. 28, 29. Rom.</hi> 1. 20. and 2. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons of this my Faith: are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe I do not find that God in his Word, threatens to condemn any for weakneſs, but for wilfulneſs; not becauſe they cannot, but becauſe they will not believe, <hi>Joh. 5. 40. Luk. 3. 34. Mat.</hi> 22. 4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe he blames, pities, and bemoans thoſe who refuſe his Counſel, and tranſgreſs his Laws, <hi>Pſal 81. 11. Luk.</hi> 13. 34.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe he calls and invites Sinners to come in and accept his Grace, which we may not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, were it impoſſible for them ſo to do, <hi>Iſa. 55. 6, 7. Rev. 22. 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe to ſuppoſe Men to be uncapable to believe and obey the Goſpel, with the helps af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded, without a Miracle (as ſome ſay,) is to ſuppoſe Men (in this matter) not to differ from Beaſts, who are capable by Miracle to do what God will have them. God could, and did make <hi>Balaam</hi>'s <hi>Aſs to ſpeak with man's voice.</hi> But Men ſhall one day know, that God made them Men and not Beaſts, if they make not themſelves ſo by beaſtly Principles and Practices. 'Tis true, that in the Goſpel many were converted to the Faith by the ſight of Miracles done without
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66029:11"/> them, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 14. and 13. 12. but the converſion of Sinners is no where called a Miracle, that I know.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe for us to ſuppoſe that God ſhould bring forth ſo gracious a diſpenſation of Love to the World, in the gift of his Son; and Chriſt to die for the World; and in love, ſend the Goſpel of this Grace to be publiſhed to the World, with gracious Invitations to accept it, and to ſtate an Intereſt therein, on impoſſible terms to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without a Miracle, and do not effect this Miracle, and yet will damn People for not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, is not only diſhonourable to God, to Chriſt, to the Goſpel, and to the Publiſhers thereof; but renders the whole glorious deſign of God therein, to be null and void, diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Men from believing thereof, it rendring them altogether uncapable, and therefore is to be denied by all ſober Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> That Faith in the Lord Jeſus is effected by the Power of God in the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>Yet 6. I do believe that whoever do obey the Lord, in the Faith of the Goſpel, in Sincerity and Truth, that it is by the Grace, Spirit, and Power of God in the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16. &amp; 5. 5. and 10. 14. by which Grace and Power they are and ſhall <hi>be kept through Faith,</hi> and a holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancy upon him <hi>unto Salvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 5.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66029:12"/> 
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 27, 28, 29. and 15. 4, 5, 6, 7, 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 39. and 125. 1. and that without this holy depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy upon, and cleaving to the Lord, in the Faith, Love, Hope, and obedience of the Goſpel, Believers may poſſibly, yea, very probably fail of, and fall from the Grace of God, and ſo miſs of the Glory promiſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 12. and 12. 15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 17. Although I do believe, that ſome are ſo known of God, and given to Chriſt, as that they have been, and ſhall be in time called, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with perſevering Grace, ſo as to obtain the end, <hi>Joh. 6. 39. Rom.</hi> 8. 29, 30. Yet theſe are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. and leave no room for any <hi>to be high-minded, but to fear an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God,</hi> Rom. 11. 20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 12. nor doth it at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the general Grace of God to Men, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 40.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons of my believing the danger of Believers failing of, and falling from the Grace of God, without their careful watch and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe with him, are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Scripture ſo plentifully ſpeaks and forewarns of the danger thereof, but never of the impoſſibility of falling. Beſides thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mentioned, among many ſee theſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. and 11. 20. 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 12. Col.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Scripture mentions ſome that were fallen, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 19. and others that were fallen, or would fall, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1.—and the reſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66029:12"/> in danger of falling, <hi>Chap. 3. 17. 1 Cor.</hi> 9. 27.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Lord himſelf, and his Apoſtles beſt knew the danger, and what Doctrine was beſt for our ſafety, and to prevent the danger, (to whom we ought to give heed, and not to our own devices) whoever taught the danger, but never the impoſſibility of falling from Grace, as before hath been proved, <hi>Mat. 10. 22. Luk.</hi> 9. 62.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the Doctrine of impoſſibility of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from Grace, being contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, muſt needs be a graceleſs and dangerous Doctrine, and that the Lord knew, and therefore hath ſo plentifully ſtated the contrary in the Scripture. If we would ſtudy a Doctrine tending to cauſe People to fail of, and fall from the Grace of God, we cannot ſtudy a more likely, than to teach impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of falling. Remove the danger, and the careful and watchful fear will be over, <hi>Rom. 11. 20. Heb.</hi> 12. 25, 28, 29, and the watchfulneſs and Prayer will quickly ceaſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 36. and it's greatly to be feared, that many (inſenſible) grow graceleſs, whilſt pleading impoſſibility of falling from Grace.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The Doctrine of poſſibility of falling from Grace, is an uncomfortable Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Doctrine which is moſt ſafe, is moſt truly comfortable. To know the danger, and to keep on our watch, being the way ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our ſafety: In that way may we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66029:13"/> ſafety, and ſo true and ſolid conſolation, <hi>Iſa. 64. 5. 2 Cor.</hi> 1. 3, 4, 5. with <hi>ver.</hi> 12. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comfort People may pretend unto, without the teſtimony of a good Conſcience in a holy walk with God and Men, they will find no ſafety therein at laſt: ſo that being the beſt way, that is moſt ſafe, and it being moſt ſafe to know the danger, (it's ſo accounted in all caſes with wiſe Men) the moſt ſafe way muſt needs be moſt truly comfortable, and the other moſt truly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and in the end uncomfortable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> And further, to ſpeak of the Reſtitution of all things, and the World to come, which in ſome Caſes I have more largely ſtated in my Anſwer to <hi>Mr. Cox</hi>'s, in my 7th <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And as I do believe the Reſtitution of all things, the new and reſtored World, and the glorious Kingdom and Raign of Chriſt with his Saints therein, mentioned in the concluſion of the ſecond Article: ſo as to the degrees, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and times of accompliſhing thereof, I do believe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it ſhall extend it ſelf to the recovery of all Mankind from the firſt Death, fallen into by the firſt Tranſgreſſion, <hi>Gen. 3. 17, 18, 19. Rom. 5. 18. 1 Cor.</hi> 15. 22. and all the World out of that Eſtate it fell into by Mans ſin, <hi>Act. 3. 21. Rom. 8. 19, 20, 21. Rev.</hi> 21. 1, 5.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66029:13"/>2. That after the Reſurrection and Judgment, it ſhall extend to the glorious Salvation of all the Faithful, with Chriſt in his Eternal Kingdom and Glory, <hi>Joh. 14. 2. Mar.</hi> 10. 30.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That this Reſtitution and Glory of the new World in all its parts, ſhall be effected by degrees, in the times appointed by the Father, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 7. and 3. 21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That at, and after the Judgment, ſhall be ſome kind of degrees of bleſſing to the Nations in general, <hi>by the Seed of the Woman that ſhall break the Serpents head, the Seed of</hi> Abraham <hi>in whom all Nations of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> (except ſuch as are by the bleſſed Seed himſelf excepted) <hi>Mat. 12. 31, 32. Prov.</hi> 1. 23, to 33. <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as wilfully rebel againſt the Light, and ſo ſin away their ſhare in this Bleſſedneſs promiſed.</p>
               <p>That there ſhall be ſome general Bleſſing for the Nations after they have born their Judgment: my Reaſons for it are,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To prove the Truth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Time.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Scripture in expreſs terms ſaith it, That in <hi>Abraham's Seed</hi> (that is, <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3. 16.) <hi>all the Nations of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 12. 3. and 22. 18. with many other Scriptures to the ſame effect, <hi>Pſal. 72. 17. Iſa.</hi> 66. 18. Though Believers are the Subjects of the ſpecial Bleſſedneſs, yet that anſwers not the general terms of the Promiſes, nor argues that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66029:14"/> none elſe ſhall have any bleſſing in the World to come. When the Scripture ſaith, <hi>All Nations, all the Families, all the Kindreds of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed in him;</hi> I ſhall in this ſay, as Mr. <hi>Increaſe Mather</hi> ſaith, on the Myſtery of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Redemption, from <hi>Rom. 11. 26. All</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be ſaved,</hi> that is, all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in oppoſition to thoſe that ſay, <hi>It intends a few of all.</hi> He ſaith <hi>Pag. 5, 6. That cannot be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Words, for the note of univerſality, [all</hi> Iſrael,] <hi>will not bear ſuch a particular reſtrained interpretation: Surely the Scripture is not wont to uſe ſuch harſh improprieties of Speech, as to ſay All, when not all, but a few only are intended. And</hi> Pag. 9. <hi>All</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be ſaved,</hi> that is, <hi>very many</hi> Iſraelits <hi>ſhall be ſaved; it noteth not only many, but moſt; it ſignifieth not only a majority, but a very full and large generality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So I ſay, That thoſe large and general Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to the Nations, of Bleſſedneſs in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed; as, <hi>All Nations of the Earth, all the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, all the Kindreds of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed in him,</hi> extends it ſelf far beyond a few, a very few in compariſon of all the Nations, but <hi>it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth not only a majority, but a very full and large generality, and not a few only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe there are many other Promiſes to the Nations in general, as properly ariſing from, and anſwering to thoſe forementioned Promiſes to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and are of like import to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66029:14"/> to be performed in time, extending far beyond the ſpecial ſaved ones, and diſtinct from them, as that, <hi>All Nations that God hath made, ſhall come and worſhip before him, and glorify his Name,</hi> Pſal. 86. 8. <hi>and that all the ends of the World ſhall remember &amp; turn to the Lord, and all the Kindreds of the Nations ſhall worſhip before him,</hi> Pſal. 22. 27. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 66. diſtinct from the Church. <hi>Ver. 18. It ſhall come, that I will gather all Nations, &amp; Tongues, and they ſhall come and ſee my Glory.</hi> Verſ. 23. <hi>All Fleſh ſhall come and worſhip before me, ſaith the Lord:</hi> and this ſhall be in the time of <hi>the new Heavens and new Earth,</hi> Verſ. 22. and <hi>Mal. 1. 11. From the riſing of the Sun, unto the going down of the ſame, my Name ſhall be great among the</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: with multitudes of like import in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that might be mentioned; and in the New Teſtament is the ſame confirmed, as the opening and explaining of the Prophecies in the Old, <hi>Act. 3. 21. Eph. 1. 10. Phil.</hi> 2. 9 10. with <hi>Rev. 5. 13. 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 10. where it's expreſt (for ſubſtance) in the terms of general and ſpecial Salvation, <hi>God is the Saviour of all Men, eſpecially of them that believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2dly. The time when this general bleſſing to Nations, in which they ſhall worſhip and ſerve the Lord, and his People ſhall be, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the World to come, at and after the Judgment is over, and not before. I believe from theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-grounds following, which will further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66029:15"/> the preſent Truth as ſtated, as likewiſe the time when it ſhall be.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe that <hi>all the Kindreds of the Earth, all the Nations that God hath made,</hi> cannot be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be bleſſed by Chriſt, and to ſerve and worſhip him, till the Reſurrection and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is over; for <hi>all Nations that God hath made,</hi> intends all that ever hath been, or ſhall be, or elſe it is not <hi>all the Nations that God hath made;</hi> but all muſt be raiſed up, and come and <hi>worſhip and ſerve the Lord, and glorify his Name,</hi> which will not (cannot) be, till after they are raiſed, and have paſt the Judgment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it muſt be in the <hi>times of the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things,</hi> in the new and reſtor'd World, that this muſt be accompliſhed upon the Nations, and therefore not till after the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Judgment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 18. with <hi>verſe</hi> 22, 23. and the new Heavens and new Earth promiſed, will not be till after the diſſolution or change of the old, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 1, 5. and it's in this time and ſtate, that all the Nations ſhall worſhip and ſerve the Lord, and therefore it muſt be after the Reſurrection and Judgment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Scripture ſaith, it ſhall be when the Lord cometh to ſit upon his Throne of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to judge the World in Righteouſneſs, that all the Nations ſhall enjoy this Priviledge and Bleſſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 7, 8. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96. 10, 13. and 98. 9. and 82. 8. <hi>Ariſe, O God, judge the Earth:</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66029:15"/> 
                  <hi>for thou ſhalt inherit all Nations.</hi> His inheriting all Nations muſt be at, and after he hath judged the Earth, and therefore at and after the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the Scripture not only ſaith, it ſhall be in the times of the new Heavens and new Earth, and in and after the Judgment, but in that time when the great Tranſgreſſours ſhall be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, where <hi>their Worm ſhall not die, neither ſhall their Fire be quenched,</hi> Iſa. 66. 18, 23. 24. In this time it is, <hi>that all Nations, and Tongues ſhall come and ſee the Glory of Chriſt, and all Fleſh ſhall come and worſhip before him,</hi> and go forth and look upon thoſe in torment; and therefore it muſt be after the Reſurrection and Judgment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Becauſe this worſhipping and ſerving of the Nations, is plainly ſtated in Scripture, to be after they have born their Judgment, and that is over and paſt, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. The Judgment is paſt and over, and after that comes <hi>the new Heavens and new Earth,</hi> into which comes down the glorious, <hi>holy City from God out of Heaven,</hi> Chap. 21. 12. And after this the Nations worſhipping and ſerving the Lord, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 26. and to this agreeth <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 8, 9. after the gathering <hi>of the Nations, and pouring out upon them the Indignation, even all the fierce Wrath,</hi> which ſutes with the ſeven laſt Plagues, in the very terms thereof, <hi>Rev. 15. 1. in which is filled up the Wrath of God,</hi> and is to be accompliſhed at and after Chriſts appearing in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66029:16"/> the Judgment, that the gathering of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and pouring out of <hi>all the fierce Wrath muſt be,</hi> Rev. 14. 14-19, 20. and after this is over, he will <hi>turn to the People a pure language, that they may all call upon the Name of the Lord, to ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> Zeph. 3. 9. which fully agreeth with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 8. and 22. 27. with many other Scriptures to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Becauſe <hi>the leaves of the Tree of Life are for the healing of the Nations,</hi> after the Judgment is over, in the eternal Eſtate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 2, 5. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19. 22. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 11, 12. which are Prophecies of the ſame time and ſtate, and to which (very probably) <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 2. relateth, and therefore it muſt be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Judgment.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Becauſe the promiſe of the peaceable time and ſtate of the World, and of the Kingdom of Chriſt therein, in which <hi>Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn War any more,</hi> Iſa. 2. 4. <hi>Mic. 4. 3. Pſal.</hi> 46. 8, 9, 10. will not be till the thouſand Years are expired, and the Judgment paſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 7, 8, 9. When the thouſand Years are expired, the Nations will be in a flame of War, therefore the peaceable time promiſed to the Nations will not (cannot) be, till this is over, when <hi>they ſhall learn War no more;</hi> and in this time and ſtate it is, that all Nations ſhall come and worſhip, therefore after the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is over, <hi>Iſa. 2. 2, 3. Mic. 4. 5. Pſal. 46. 10. Mal.</hi> 1. 11.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66029:16"/>8. Becauſe it's more than probable, that all the Scriptures that promiſe to Chriſt an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> do relate to his Kingdom and Raign in the World to come, and that too, after all his Enemies are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and viſibly ſubjected under him, which will not be till after the Reſurrection and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is over and paſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 23, 24, 25. which expreſsly relates to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. 1. and that his right-hand Kingdom on his Fathers Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 21. is an intervening Glory, as a preſent reward of his Sufferings, and for performance of his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory-office, till his own Kingdom take place, which will be his higheſt viſible Glory, and of which <hi>he is in expectation,</hi> Heb. 10. 13. And hence it likewiſe appears, that the ſervice and worſhip of the World will not be, till this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Kingdom take place, in which all Nations ſhall ſerve him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 8, 9, 10, 11. It muſt be <hi>when all Enemies are made his Footſtool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Becauſe (as before I ſaid) this general Salvation by Chriſt in the World to come, is that which tends ſo wonderfully to exalt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the glory of his Sufferings, and Death for the World, and the deſign of God therein. The more uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal the deſign was, the more of Grace, and the more glorious to the name of God and Chriſt, and the narrowing thereof to a few only; and all the reſt of Mankind, with the whole Creation eternally to periſh, not only contradicts the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66029:17"/> truth of the whole Volum of the Book of God, but wonderfully derogates from the glory of God and Chriſt deſigned in this wonderful Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, <hi>Joh. 13. 30, 32. Iſa.</hi> 6. 3. with <hi>Joh. 12. 41. Pſal.</hi> 72. 19.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Becauſe it's that in which the Glory of the Kingdom and Raign of Chriſt in the World to come is ſo wonderfully concerned: for <hi>the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a King is in the multitude of People,</hi> Prov. 14. 28. If a King ſhould have a glorious Queen (only,) and have no People, no Subjects, where would his honour be? The Church is (and ſhall be) the Lord's Queen, the royal and eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of Chriſt, <hi>the King and Lord of Glory,</hi> Pſal. 45. 9. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thy right-hand did ſtand the Queen in the Gold of</hi> Ophir.</p>
               <p>It's true, the Queen is a Subject to the King, yet above all others with the King, and neareſt to him, as his royal Conſort, bearing part (at leaſt) of the honour of Government. But if the King have not his other Attendants, his Royal Council, with multitude of Subjects in variety of degrees, where will his honour be?</p>
               <p>So the Lord and King Chriſt Jeſus, eſpecially of the new and reſtored World, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. 9. who then ſhall be viſibly <hi>Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,</hi> Rev. 19. 16. and ſhall have all things ſutable to ſuch a Kingdom; yea, far ſurpaſſing all the Glory of the moſt glorious Monarchs that ever were in this World as Types of this his Glory;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66029:17"/> yea, <hi>Solomon</hi> (the moſt famous Type of Chriſt, in this his moſt glorious reign) in all his glory came infinitely ſhort of him.</p>
               <p>For firſt, His Church, his Spouſe, yea, his then married Wife and Queen, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 7. ſhall keep Court with him in the glorious, holy City, and ſhall reign with him for ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The glorious holy Angels ſhall be his and his Queens Attendants, <hi>Heb. 1. 6. Rev.</hi> 5. 11. for the Church his Wife and Queen ſhall be united nearer to him by far than the glorious holy Angels, <hi>Heb. 2. 16. Eph.</hi> 5. 30. who ſhall be his and his Churches Attendants.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, All the World ſhall be raiſed by him, and be his Subjects, in various ſtates and degrees, and ſhall worſhip and ſerve him (as before hath been proved,) and all as an effect of giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Sacrifice for <hi>the Life of the World,</hi> Joh. 6. 51. 1 <hi>Joh. 4. 14. Phil.</hi> 2. 6. to 11. and in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth a very great part of the glory of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World to come; for allow him no Subjects in his Kingdom, beſides his married Wife and Queen, you take away a very great part of his Kingdom and Glory.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And finally, this bleſſing of the Nations in general in their worſhipping and ſerving the Lord Chriſt, muſt and ſhall be in the World to come, at and after the Reſurrection and Judgment, not only from the former grounds
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66029:18"/> ſtated, but becauſe this Glory ſhall be effected at and after the ſounding of the ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. 6, 7. when the time of this World ſhall be no more, <hi>but the myſtery of God ſpoken of by the Prophets ſhall be finiſhed.</hi> And what is this <hi>myſtery ſpoken of by the Prophets,</hi> but <hi>the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things, ſpoken of by all the holy Prophets that have been ſince the World began?</hi> Act. 3. 21. the glory of the World to come, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt therein. Which myſtery is more fully explained at the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 15. to which <hi>Chap.</hi> 10 6, 7. refers, <hi>And the ſeventh Angel ſounded, and there were great Voices in Heaven, ſaying, The Kingdoms of this World are become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt; and he ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi> Here is <hi>the finiſhing of the myſtery of God, ſpoken of by all the holy Prophets ſince the World began.</hi> The breaking of the Serpents head by the Womans Seed, the Bleſſing promiſed to all Nations in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, the glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Seed and Son of <hi>David</hi> (promiſed) over the whole World, ſhall then be finiſhed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 11, 17. when <hi>the Glory of the Lord ſhall fill the whole Earth,</hi> verſ. 19. <hi>and all Nations ſhall worſhip before him,</hi> Rev. 15. 4.</p>
               <p>That whatever Bleſſing the Nations in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral may obtain at that day, as it ſhall be after they have paſt the Judgment, ſo their ſtate in general will be a ſtate of Service, Bondage, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66029:18"/> Slavery, compared with the ſtate of the married Wife, <hi>Iſa. 60. 14. Zech.</hi> 14. 9, 16, to 19. <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. 16, 17. yet far excelling thoſe that ſhall be under the loweſt and deepeſt Judgment, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 24.</p>
               <p>That as the World to come, and whole Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution ſhall be all effected by the Death, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Life, and Power of Chriſt; ſo his Kingdom and Glory therein (over the World,) with his married Wife the Church, ſhall be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and never have an end; it ſhall be a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and World without end, <hi>Dan. 7. 14, 27. Iſa. 45. 17. Rev.</hi> 11. 15. and 22. 5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 33. I ſhall (nor need) in this ſay no more, but only offer three things to ſerious conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where is any Scripture that doth declare an end of the World to come, and of the Kingdom of Chriſt therein? If not, but fully the contrary, then it muſt needs be mans invention ſo to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the Eternal Life and Glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, be not in the World to come? <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. 30. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 29. and if ſo, then where is any promiſe in the Scripture of Eternal Life in another World? and if not, then whether thoſe that ſuppoſe an end of the World to come, do not withal ſuppoſe an end of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of the Life and Glory of the Saints promiſed in the Goſpel therein?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Where is any Scripture that doth expreſly or impliedly aſſert the going away of Chriſt with all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66029:19"/> his Saints to Heaven after the Reſurrection and Judgment is over? and if there be none, then whether we may not ſafely conclude it to be but the device of Men, and to have no truth in it, it being ſo contrary to the Glory of his Kingdom and Government here below in the new and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored World.</p>
               <p>I know but two things, that is, or can be ſaid in this matter.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That the Scripture exhorteth <hi>to lay up for our ſelves treaſure in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 6. 20. to be <hi>ſeeking after, and ſetting our Affections on things above,</hi> Col. 3. 1, 2. that the <hi>incorruptible Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that fadeth not away, is reſerved in Heaven,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 4. that Chriſt will <hi>come again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his People to himſelf, that where he is, there they may be alſo,</hi> Joh. 14. 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To this I ſay, It's true, that our All is in Heaven, our God, our Chriſt, and the Glory to come is all in Heaven, is fully granted. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſhall come down from thence into the new and reſtored World. Chriſt ſhall come down, and the glorious <hi>Holy City ſhall come down from God out of Heaven, and the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with Men,</hi> Rev. 3. 12. and 21. 1, 2. and ſo the Saints, Heaven, and Glory ſhall be here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, in the Holy City, into which Chriſt will receive them with himſelf. And this is explain'd 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 5. It's ready to be revealed in the laſt time,</hi> that is, revealed from Heaven, coming down
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66029:19"/> from God out of Heaven, as <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt from Heaven, is called <hi>the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">II. It may be, and is objected, that it's ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 28. That he <hi>muſt deliver up the Kingdom to the Father, and God ſhall be all in all, and the Son himſelf ſhall be ſubject;</hi> which ſeems to import an end of the Son's Kingdom, and ſo probably a going away to Heaven with all his Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. We may not underſtand one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo, as to contradict all others that ſpeak of the ſame thing, that can be neither true nor ſafe; and all other Scriptures that ſpeak of the Kingdom of Chriſt in the World to come, ſay, it ſhall be eternal, without end; and therefore we may not underſtand, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 28. ſo as is contrary thereunto, that can be neither true nor ſafe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. That Scripture rightly underſtood, explains it ſelf, ſo as will comport with all the Scriptures that ſpeak of the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That the World to come, and the Kingdom of Chriſt therein, ſhall be Eternal.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Becauſe it's the preſent Kingdom of the Son, as exerciſed at the right-hand of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſhall be delivered up, and not his own Perſonal, Viſible Kingdom, as upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> that muſt be for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 7. and that it is his preſent Kingdom at the right-hand of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66029:20"/> God, is clear, <hi>v. 24, 25. for he muſt reign till he hath put all Enemies under his feet,</hi> herein alluding to <hi>Pſa.</hi> 110. 1. and this Reign is after his coming from Heaven, and the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23, 24. and is apparent, that it's this Reign and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that ſhall be given up <hi>when all his Enemies are his Footſtool,</hi> of which <hi>he is in expectation, Heb.</hi> 10. 13. for in this right-hand Kingdom ſhall he be, after he is come from Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 64. and after the firſt Reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 23, 24. and till the whole Conqueſt over all Enemies is over, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 5, 6, 7. and of Death the laſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which will not be till the thouſand Years Reign and Judgment be over, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 14. for until the whole work is finiſhed, and the laſt Enemy deſtroyed, which is Death, he is ſtill in his right-hand Kingdom, in the proper ſenſe of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 28. and hath not given it up to God the Father, for that is not to be done till all is made ſubject to him, and then ſhall he reign over all as the viſible King and Lord of the whole Earth, <hi>Heb 2. 8. Iſa. 54. 5. Zech.</hi> 14. 9.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) It's apparent that it intends not the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up of his own viſible Kingdom after all is viſibly made ſubject to him, becauſe it is the higheſt Glory mentioned in Scripture that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned him, of which he <hi>is in expectation,</hi> Heb. 2. 8. and 10. 13. for all except the Father himſelf muſt be viſibly put under him, but <hi>he is excepted that did put all things under him,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 27.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66029:20"/>
               <p>So that the ſum of all is, to let us to know, that in this top-glory of the Son of God, and the Son of <hi>David,</hi> when all things are put under him, and made ſubject to him, and that he is the viſible King and Lord of the whole Earth, of which he is in expectation; that the Father is excepted herein, only himſelf will be above him, and the Son ſubject to him, in this his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Kingdom; that the Father will rule eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in and by his Son, in this his viſible Glory; and in this ſenſe will the Father be all in his own Kingdom, being delivered up by the Son, <hi>and in all,</hi> in his Son's Kingdom, though the Son be the only viſible Lord thereof. And thus God the Father will not loſe his Glory in his Son's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but then ſhall be perfectly performed that ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Joh 5. 22, 23. that all Men ſhall honour the Son, even as they honour the Father,</hi> and this Glory of the Father in the Son's Kingdom ſhall be no diminution at all to the Son's Glory, but rather the augmentation thereof. As the Son's Kingdom at his Fathers right-hand, is no diminution to his Fathers Glory, ſo ſhall not the Father's Kingdom and Glory (as exerciſed in, by and with the Son) any whit diminiſh either the Sons or the Saints Glory, but increaſe it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And hence it is, that it's ſometimes called the Fathers Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 10. and 13. 43. and 26. 29. and ſometimes the Son's Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:66029:21"/> 16. 28. <hi>Luk. 22. 29. Joh. 18. 36. 2 Pet.</hi> 1. 11. All which tends to clear this matrer, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Kingdom of Chriſt, when all is brought under him, in the World to come, ſhall be eternal, the Father reigning in and by him. As he now reigns with the Father on his Throne, and ſo ſhall continue till all his Enemies be made ſubject to him, ſo ſhall his Father reign with him on his Throne. And as the Father ſhall <hi>be All</hi> on his own Throne in Heaven, ſo ſhall he be <hi>in all</hi> in his Son's Kingdom here below, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 10, 11. and indeed the top-glory, both of the Father, Son, and Saints, deſigned in the Reſtitution by Jeſus Chriſt, will iſſue here, 1 <hi>Tim. 6. 14, 15, 16. Mat.</hi> 19. 28.</p>
               <p>And in this Eſtate ſhall Chriſt be both King and Prieſt upon his Throne for ever, <hi>he being a Prieſt for ever, after the order of</hi> Melchiſedeck, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 6. and 7. 17. <hi>conſecrated ſo for evermore,</hi> verſ. 28. The middle Perſon between God and Men, between the Father and his Church, as the head thereof, in whom their ſtanding and ſervice ſhall be perpetually preſented and accepted, and the ſervice of the Nations ſhall have acceptance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 7. And thus ſhall the blood of Chriſt be known to be the Blood of the new and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, <hi>Heb</hi> 13. 20. and on this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Covenant, the everlaſting State, World, and Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall be founded and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 12, 13. and 22. 1, 3.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:66029:21"/>
               <p>That as all is founded in the one Sacrifice, ſo it is and ſhall be all effected by a new and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant (in and with the Lord Chriſt, who was this one Sacrifice) and not by the old.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That with <hi>Adam</hi> is broken, and could do nothing of this kind, That brought in Death, and the Curſe upon Man, and upon the whole Creation for man's ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 16. to 19. but could not recover from that Eſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Law could not do it, being but a figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Miniſtration, it could do nothing in this matter, but leave all under Curſe and Death ſtill, making nothing perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 19. and 11. 40. but it muſt all be effected by a new Covenant of Grace and Life in the <hi>ſecond Man, who is the Lord from Heaven,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. and 22. 18. <hi>Cal. 3. 17. Life and immortality is brought to light through the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 10.</p>
               <p>The myſtery of Iniquity having gotten very much footing in the World by confounding the Covenants, making them all but one, and not diſtinguiſhing according to the truth thereof. Much of Goſpel-truth, relating to the Church here in this World, hath been clouded thereby, as well as the Glory that is to come; as likewiſe many dangerous Errors proceed therefrom, ſo that it's no marvel that the great Judgments threatned to come upon the profeſſing part of the World in the latter days, is for <hi>breaking the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant,</hi> Iſa. 24. 5.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:66029:22"/>
               <p>That the Kingdoms of this World are given to the Princes and Powers thereof, (as ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate unto Chriſt) until he come <hi>to take to himſelf his great Power, and to reign, at which the Nations will be angry, becauſe they muſt then be judged,</hi> Rev. 11. 17, 18. and that it is the ordinance of God, and duty of his People, to be ſubject to them in all lawful things of worldly concern, <hi>Rom. 13. 1, 2, 3. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15. and patiently to bear and ſuffer whatever they meet with from Men, for the name and ſake of Chriſt, till that day come, <hi>Act. 14. 22. 2 Theſſ. 1. 7. Jam.</hi> 5. 7, 8.</p>
               <p>Thus have I endeavoured to give a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my Faith in the great matters of <hi>the glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God:</hi> And if I muſt be accounted by ſome an Heretick herein, I hope I ſhall gladly bear it, for the ſake of Chriſt my dear Lord, till the great day of deciſion come, when all Mens Faith and Works ſhall be made manifeſt, of what ſort it is; and then, every one that hath been right for God, <hi>ſhall have praiſe of him:</hi> and ſo I ſhall conclude this with theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Scriptures.</p>
               <p>2 Pet. 3. 11. <hi>Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, what manner of Perſons ought we to be in all holy converſation and godlineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 14. <hi>Wherefore (beloved) ſeeing ye look for ſuch things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſa. 32. 4. <hi>The tongue of the ſtammerers ſhall be</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:66029:22"/> 
                  <hi>ready to ſpeak plain, and the heart alſo of the raſh ſhall underſtand knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chap. 29. 24. <hi>They that erred in ſpirit, ſhall come to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and they that murmured, ſhall learn Doctrine.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>Pſal. 116. 10. <hi>I believed, therefore have I ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Luk. 2. 29, 30, 31. <hi>Now, Lord, let thy Servant depart in Peace; for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which thou haſt prepared before the face of all People, a Light to lighten the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy People</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>Mat. 24. 14. <hi>And this Goſpel of the Kingdom ſhall be preached in all the World, for a witneſs unto all Nations, and then ſhall the end come,</hi> Rev. 14. 6, 7.</p>
               <q>The Church with whom I walk, is united in the ſubſtance of this Faith, before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66029:23"/>
            <head>The Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>A Confeſſion of Faith lately publiſhed from <hi>London,</hi> providentially coming to my hands; and contrary to my expectation, finding ſuch things therein, as was and is truly grievous to me, it being inconſiſtent with the true Faith and Religion of God, I could not in good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, both towards God and Man, paſs it by, without ſaying ſomething thereunto.</p>
            <p>In which I find, under the name of funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principles of Faith, no leſs than ſeven things of ſpecial note, contrary thereunto, moſt of which I have before detected, and them I ſhall but only name; ſo that though there are many good Truths ſcattered therein, yet theſe contrary, unſound, and unſcriptural notions contradict and undo them all.</p>
            <p>As 1. Abſolute Reprobation of the World from Eternity alone from the free Will of God, though not plainly in terms expreſt, but more covertly and hiddenly, yet abſolutely and fully ſtated; for they ſay, that <hi>God hath immutably decreed all things, whatſoever comes to paſs;</hi> and that <hi>he elected or predeſtinated a certain number of Angels and Men to Eternal Life, to which there can be no addition,</hi> &amp;c. which ſtates abſolute Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66029:23"/> to all the World beſides, by an eternal Decree before the World was.</p>
            <p>2. Chriſt dying to redeem the Elect only, and that none elſe can poſſibly obtain; which not only denieth the truth of God's Love to the World, and Chriſt's <hi>giving himſelf for the life of the World,</hi> but contains in it the abſoluteſt Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the World that can be ſtated: for if Chriſt died not for them, it's impoſſible they ſhould be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 12.</p>
            <p>3. Impoſſiblity for any to believe, with the Goſpel helps that God affordeth, without a mighty miraculous power; miſunderſtanding, and ſo wronging the Scripture for its confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>4. Juſtification by Faith without Works, and not by Faith neither, as the Scripture ſtates it, <hi>viz.</hi> as the conditions and terms of our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in <hi>Pag. 40. Of Juſtification,</hi> they ſay, <hi>it is not by imputing Faith it ſelf, the act of Believing, or any other Evangelical obedience, as their Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; Faith is the alone inſtrument of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as of receiving Chriſt:</hi> whereas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, Abraham <hi>believed God, and it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs,</hi> Gen. 15. 6. and Rom. 4. 3, 5. <hi>His Faith is counted for Righteouſneſs,</hi> ver. 23, 24. But they ſay plainly, No, it is not imputed, but only an Inſtrument, and what that is I do not know, nor is the Scripture acquainted with ſuch language; but I leave the Reader to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66029:24"/> believe the Scripture, or them, which he pleaſe.</p>
            <p>5. Impoſſibility of falling from Grace, which is contrary to the whole current of Scripture, as before hath been ſhewed.</p>
            <p>6. In <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. of the Decrees of God, <hi>That God hath from all Eternity decreed in himſelf all things whatſoever comes to paſs,</hi> &amp;c. and that this Decree is <hi>immutable and unchangeable,</hi> ariſing not from <hi>knowledge of what would be, but from his own determinate Will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. of Divine Providence, <hi>That this his determinate Counſel extends it ſelf to the firſt fall, and all other ſinful actions, both of Angels and Men (and that not by a bare permiſſion) which alſo he moſt wiſely and powerfully boundeth and otherwiſe ordereth and governeth, in a manifold diſpenſation to his moſt holy ends, yet ſo as the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their acts proceed only of the Creatures and not from God, who being moſt righteous, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is nor can be the approver of ſin,</hi> Pſal. 50. 21. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 16. Theſe laſt words are true, and contradict all the reſt as moſt Heretical and falſe, for he cannot but approve his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees.</p>
            <p>In theſe Poſitions the Myſtery of Iniquity ſeems to be perfected, including a perfection of falſhood, impiety, and abominations in them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The abuſe of the Scriptures for proof of this horrid Doctrine, not one of the Scriptures mentioned having any ſuch thing in them, nor
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66029:24"/> indeed may we imagine any ſuch thing to be in the holy Word of the holy God, without blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy againſt him. What, that God hath eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally decreed <hi>in himſelf all things whatſoever comes to paſs? the determinate Counſel extending it ſelf to all the ſinful actions, both of Angels and Men?</hi> What, the Decreer thereof, and yet not the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover of his own Decrees?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But we have a way to diſtinguiſh between the Actions and the ſinfulneſs of the Actions. God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed all Actions, and all Actions in themſelves are ſimply good, becauſe acted in his Power, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Decrees; but the ſinfulneſs of the Action is the Creatures, of which God is no Approver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, I think it will require more Logick and Rhetorick thus rightly to diſtinguiſh, than all the Perſons in the World of this opinion will be able to find out.</p>
            <p>Hath God decreed the act of Murther and not the ſin? and ſo of Adultery, Witchcraft, and all other abominations? is not the act it ſelf the ſin? if there were no ſuch act, there would be no ſuch ſin; therefore let them divide the act from the ſin if they can, the act to be God's Decree, and the ſin the Creatures, and God no approver thereof, though he decreed it, as they ſay.</p>
            <p>But 1. To prove that God hath <hi>decreed all things whatſoever comes to paſs, all ſinful Actions, both of Angels and Men,</hi> Iſa. 46. 10. <hi>Eph. 1. 11. Heb.</hi> 6. 17. is referred to; all which Scriptures
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66029:25"/> ſpeak only of God's own Works, and Counſel determined, and declared, eſpecially relative to his Goſpel-work of Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, and not his determining all the ſinful actions of Angels and Men, as a weak capacity may eaſily diſcern. So the like of <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 18.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 23. &amp; 4. 17, 28. Firſt, The Scriptures do not ſay, that God decreed them to crucifie his Son. <hi>But that he was delivered by the determinate Counſel and foreknowledge of God,</hi> for them to do unto him what he before knew they would do. He determined that his Son ſhould give himſelf for the life of the World, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knew that the <hi>Jews</hi> with the reſt would do that Work, and he determined to give him up to them, and they <hi>by wicked hands crucified him.</hi> And therein he bounded their actions to his own Counſel before determined.</p>
            <p>But, Secondly, What ever the Divine Decree might be in this matter, is not material for proof of the thing aſſerted, if we ſhould ſuppoſe that God decreed them to do it, without reſpect had to any condition in them as the cauſe thereof, which can never be proved.</p>
            <p>Yet it being ſo great a Myſtery of Grace, and that on which the Life of the World depended, I ſhall chooſe rather to loſe my ſelf in this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Decree, leaving it to God alone, than from this Example and bottomleſs Myſtery, to draw up ſo impious a Concluſion; that God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66029:25"/> hath from his own Will from all Eternity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, by an immutable Decree, all the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs both of Devils and Men, that ever hath been, is, or ſhall be in the World. And as for the Scriptures referr'd to, for proving God's ordering all things by his Providence, for the accompliſhing of his Decrees, relative to the ſins of <hi>both Angels and Men, Providence powerfully over-ruleth all things,</hi> for the accompliſhment thereof, 2 <hi>King. 19. 28. Pſ.</hi> 76. 10. the prudent may eaſily diſcern how far wide it is from proving this matter. And as for <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 15, 18, 22, 23. ſo frequently referr'd to, I have (I ſuppoſe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid enough to diſcover their fallacy in ſo applying thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> to underſtand theſe ſeveral ſayings of the Apoſtle, contrary to the whole volumn of the Book of God, and contrary to the very Name, Nature, and Truth of God, muſt needs be very impious; and very probably theſe may be ſome of the <hi>hard things to be underſtood, written by the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>in his Epiſtle mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 15, 16. <hi>which they that are unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unſtable, wreſt to their own deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that this Principle not only abuſeth God in his Decrees, to decree all ſinful actions, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in his Providence, and Government, <hi>in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully over-ruling and ordering all things,</hi> and to ſo bad an end, and abuſing the holy Scripture for proof thereof.</p>
            <p>2. As it's unſcriptural, and ſo belieth God, ſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66029:26"/> its impious, laying all the ſins and wickedneſs in the World, both of Devils and Men at God's door: for if he hath decreed all, and <hi>that not by a bare permiſſion, but wiſely and powerfully order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to his own ends;</hi> there is (then) no avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, but the Decree muſt be accompliſhed. So that by this Doctrine all the ſins in the World are committed by the unchangeable Decree of God, and powerful over-ruling Providence, in order thereunto. And ſo, as an effect hereof, all the Judgments and Plagues threatned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, in this Life and that which is to come, as a puniſhment of ſin, flows from the eternal and immutable Decree of God, and ſo impoſſible by any means to be prevented: which is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious to imagin and contrary to the Scripture, <hi>Jer. 18. 7, 8. Iſa.</hi> 55. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It renders God to take pleaſure in the Sin and Judgment of his Creatures: for in the accompliſhing of his own free immutable Will, muſt be his ſupream and abſolute pleaſure; that which he hath immutably determined, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, muſt needs be well pleaſing to him: So that it renders God to take pleaſure in the Sin and Judgment of Men, contrary to his own word. 1. For Sin, he hateth it, and therefore decreed it not, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. 16, to 19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2. And for Judgment, he pitieth poor ſinners who wilfully expoſe themſelves thereunto, <hi>Hoſ. 11. 8, 9. Luk. 19. 41, 42, 43, 44. Lam. 3. 33. He doth not afflict</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66029:26"/> 
               <hi>willingly, nor grieve the Children of Men.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he decreed it not, any otherwiſe than as a puniſhment for Sin, which might by repentance have been avoided, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. 8. So that it not only renders God by his Eternal Decree, to be the firſt cauſe of all the Sin, of all the Hatred, Wrath, Murders, Adulteries, Drunkenneſs, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Idolatries, Witchcrafts and Rebellions in the World, and ſo of all the Judgments, which are the effect thereof, but that its well pleaſing and delightful to him, it being the effect of his eternal and unchangeable Decree, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his word, moſt and impious to imagine.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It's that which renders God to be contradictory and inconſiſtent to himſelf, and uncertain in any part of his Word and Will to Men; it renders it full of contradiction, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand one thing and hath decreed the contrary; to command Men to believe, repent and be holy, and hath decreed the contrary; hath decreed all the Wickedneſs and Abominations in the World, and yet commands the contrary; and will damn people for breach of his Commands, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf decreed from all eternity that they ſhould not keep, which is moſt impious to imagine.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And ſo it renders his Word (which is his abſolute revealed Will to Men) to be incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and ſo deſtroyeth the ground of Faith, which is the truth and faithfulneſs of God in his Word: for if it were true, that he commands
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66029:27"/> one thing, and hath decreed another directly contrary to it, by the ſame rule and reaſon, may he promiſe one thing, when he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed the contrary, eſpecially all his Promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on condition of doing his Precepts, and if his Decrees be contrary to his Precepts, ſo may they be contrary to his Promiſes, and ſo there be no truth, neither in his Precepts nor his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: and it lays a foundation for to teach people ſo to believe, and therefore its moſt impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to be imagined.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, It's that which renders the moſt wicked and vile, to be the trueſt and beſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God: for, 1ſt, (If this were true) they do his Will moſt freely, and naturally, and ſuch are reputed to be his beſt Servants, whereas (as is by them confeſt) Believing, Repenting and Obeying the Lord in his revealed Will, is hard and difficult, and is attended (at beſt) with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weakneſſes, and ſometimes, in ſome things unwillingneſs; whereas the others ſerve him in his abſolute decreed Will, moſt freely and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily. 2. They ſerve him moſt perfectly, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his decreed Will in all things, (whereas the Saints are attended with many failings and coming ſhort in ſervice) the others not, and therefore muſt needs be the beſt Sarvants of God, if this Doctrine were true, which is moſt impious to imagine.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, It's that which renders God in his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66029:27"/> eternal Will, to take more pleaſure in ſin and wickedneſs, than in holineſs, in that he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed ſo much ſin and wickedneſs to be in the World, and ſo little holineſs, which is moſt impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to imagine.</p>
            <p>Eightly, It's that which renders God to love Judgment more than Mercy, having from his own Will freely decreed ſo much Sin, Judgment and Damnation to the World, and ſo little Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Salvation to Men; which is contrary to his Word and Oath, <hi>Exod. 34. 6, 7. Ezek. 33. 11. Joh.</hi> 3. 16. and is therefore moſt impious to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, It's that which tends to end all Chriſtian Religion in the World: for if God Command one thing, and hath Decreed another, it leaves us at a loſs in all things: no Man knows when he doth his Will, and when not: <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all Men every where to repent;</hi> yet by this Doctrine, hath decreed the Sin and Damnation of (almoſt) all the World; he commands to pray for all Men, yet hath decreed the Sin and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of (almoſt) all Men. It rationally ends all repentance for Sin, all reproofs for Sin, all blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Men for Sin, none can be reproveable for any of their actions, either Saints or Sinners, their works being all decreed of old, it's all the holy Will of God: If his decreed Will be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then the keeping thereof muſt be holy, and ſo no ſuch thing as Sin in the World, and ſo it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66029:28"/> neceſſarily turns all thoſe ſayings in Scripture, that manifeſt God's diſpleaſure againſt Sin into a lie, as that <hi>he is angry with the wicked every day, Pſal.</hi> 7. 11. Yea and angry (and ſometimes <hi>very angry)</hi> with his own People, becauſe of Sin, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1. 31. and 9. 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 1. which if Sin be the effecting of his abſolute decreed Will, it's impoſſible to be true, that he ſhould be angry with any for doing his freely decreed Will. So that this Principle leaves no room for any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and therefore is moſt impious.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, If God immutably determined all ſinful acts, it lays a foundation for Rantiſm, Atheiſm, and all manner of filthineſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs in the World. And indeed had I met with ſuch a Principle from the Ranters, I ſhould not have marvelled, it being the foundation of their practice, <hi>viz.</hi> that all is the decreed Will of God, and therefore all is alike good, and ſo, no ſuch thing as Sin in the World; this being the foundation of ſo horrid a building, it is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious to aſſert or imagine.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, It's that which renders God to be worſe to Men than the Devil, and that both in reſpect to Sin and Puniſhment. 1. Of Sin, the Devil can but tempt unto it, and may be reſiſted, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 7. but the eternal Decree of God is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible, that muſt be done. 2. The Devil can by temptation, but endeavour by ſin to fit Men for Judgment; but by this Doctrine, the eternal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66029:28"/> Decree, hath deſtinated the world, both to Sin and Judgment, without all hope or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble help, which if the Devil believed (which with-out doubt he dos not, but knows the contrary) it would make him a very ſluggard, his work being already effected by eternal Decree, he need not <hi>go about like a roaring Lion ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> if all were devoured by the eternal and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtible Decree! which were it true, O, Wo to the World that they have ſuch a God! which is moſt impious to imagine. And as for what they ſay, that God does not force any to ſin, but leaves them to the liberty of their wills, helps not, for the Decree muſt be effected.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, And finally, as an effect of all, It ſtrikes a deadly blow to the whole Name, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Being of God, as opened to us both in his Word and by his Works.</p>
            <p>As 1. In his Holineſs, that he <hi>is moſt holy;</hi> that <hi>Holy and Reverent is his name; that he loveth Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and hateth Sin and Wickedneſs,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing elſe but Sin, and for Sins ſake: but this aſſerts all the unholineſs, ſins and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World, both of Devils and Men, to be his birth from all eternity, by an eternal and immutable Decree.</p>
            <p>2. In his Goodneſs and Mercy to Men, the Scripture teſtifieth that he is <hi>good to all,</hi> that he loved the World in the gift of his Son: but this kills this Doctrine of Goodneſs and Mercy to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66029:29"/> the World, aſſerting the Sin and Judgment of the World eſtabliſhed by an immutable Decree before the World was, which renders the great deſign of God in the Creation, to be the Sin and Judgment of the World, without all hope or help, and in ſending his Son to effect the ſame, which is moſt impious to imagine.</p>
            <p>3. In his Juſtice. The Scripture ſaith, that <hi>all his ways are judgment, a God of truth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniquity, juſt and right is he,</hi> Deut. 32. 4. But this faſtens on him the greateſt injuſtice imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, to determine Men by a forcible and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Decree (before they were) to ſin againſt his Law, that ſo he might take Juſtice on them. Which likewiſe aſmuch derogates from his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in finding no more righteous a way to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify his Juſtice, than by enforcing Men to ſin by an irreſiſtible Decree, and over-ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in order thereunto, that ſo Juſtice might take place upon them. What ſuch a thing would be accounted among Men, I need not ſpeak.</p>
            <p>But here it will be objected, That God is under no Law, his own Will is his Law, and whatever he willeth is good and righteous; and therefore, what have we to do to queſtion his Will and Work, or to ſay unto him, <hi>what doeſt thou?</hi> Rom. 9. 14 to 22. hath enough in it to confirm this, and to ſtop all Mouths in this matter.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:66029:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It's true, the Will of God is his Law, and whatever he wills is juſt and right. Yet 2. It behoves us to underſtand, that ſuch is the holineſs of his Nature and Name, that he can will nothing which is contrary thereunto. And 3. That ſuch is his Truth and Faithfulneſs, that he never did nor can will any thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Word, <hi>Rom. 3. 3, 4. Tit.</hi> 1. 2. That though he be under no Law of Mans making, yet he is under the Law of his own Name and Nature, of his own revealed Word and Will, and thoſe who ſay otherwiſe, end all ground of Faith and Religion. And as for <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. I have ſaid enough to that already, it not relating to his eternal Decrees, but his preſent actings towards Men, in way of Judgment for former Iniquity; and otherwiſe to underſtand it, is contrary to the Name, Nature, and Truth of God in his Word; and therefore is impious ſo to imagine.</p>
            <p>4. And it ſtrikes as deeply at the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God in his Word, which preſents us with his <hi>being good to all,</hi> and with his love to all, in which he ſweareth, that he <hi>hath no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the death of the Wicked,</hi> but this gives him the lye in all, aſſerting an eternal Decree both of Sin and Death, before the World was: <hi>But let God be true, and every Man a Lyar,</hi> in this matter.</p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured (though very briefly) to open this great Myſtery of Iniquity, and had
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66029:30"/> it not been ſtated as a Foundation-Principle of Faith (though tending to end all Faith) and clothed in ſo fine a dreſs, as making ſo much for the exaltation of God in his Name, and for the conſolation of Chriſtians, had at preſent ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it; and all ariſing from, and as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that untimely born Monſter, <hi>Abſolute Reprobation of the World by an immutable Decree before ever it had a Being.</hi> And from hence, as the Reprobation was decreed, ſo muſt the Sin, to make the Reprobation certain and ſure; and from hence comes in the denial of God's love to the World, and Chriſt's giving himſelf a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the ſins of the World; all is to confirm this monſtrous Birth, with ſeveral other things that I could name that flows from it, as the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Some may ſay, O Sir, you are too raſh, you out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> run the Bounds of Moderation, and your own Principle, which is for Moderation, and the Goſpel-ſpirit of Love and Peace; and beſides, the Aſſerters of this Principle intend no ſuch things as you ſay are included therein, but do often declare in other of their Articles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be againſt Sin, and for Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I am of the ſame Mind, and have more Charity towards the Perſons concerned herein, than to think they really intend all that is included in this Principle, and therefore ſhall not ſay they are Hereticks, though the Principles in themſelves are as deeply heretical as any can poſſibly be.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:66029:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Their many ſayings to the contrary, argues either, 1. Their ignorance of their own Principles, not underſtanding the true nature and tendency thereof, it being truly and really the open door to Rantiſm. At this very door it entred (and they have anew ſet it open again;) They concluded that God having decreed all things, then all acts muſt be alike good and pleaſing to God, that there could be no ſuch thing in the World as Sin; and indeed, if it were true, that <hi>all things whatſoever come to paſs in the World,</hi> were God's birth, by virtue of his eternal Decree, then all muſt be good, and the Ranters in the right Religion, which far be it from any ſober Chriſtian to imagine. Or, 2. It argues their contradiction (for indeed, if they held it without contradiction, it muſt needs be the moſt damnable Principle in the World) to aſſert God to be Author of all things whatſoever, by an eternal and immutable Decree, and yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome of thoſe things to be evil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſinful, and damnable, and God not to be the Approver thereof, yet his own decreed act is the higheſt contradiction and irreconcilable to it ſelf; nor will that vain device any whit help in this matter (as before I ſhewed) that the act is God's, and ſo good, but the ſin is the Creatures, till they can either religiouſly or rationally diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the act and the ſin, the act being the ſin; were there no ſuch acts, there could be no ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66029:31"/> ſins, <hi>ſin being the tranſgreſſion of the Law;</hi> it will ſtand as the greateſt and moſt irreconcilable contradiction as can be imagined, or the greateſt Blaſphemy that can be againſt God.</p>
            <p>3. It being the over-ruling Article, ſtated next to the Being of God. All the reſt muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by this, and ſtoop to it; nothing may be underſtood in the reſt that is contrary to this, this being the foundation of all, and indeed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doeth and contradicteth all the reſt at once: for all decreed acts are good, and ſo there can be no Sin, and ſo no Judgment; and ſo ſaith the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple it ſelf, from whence they learned it; and as I could name, <hi>that there is nothing Sin as it is the Decree of God, that the things which he decreed are moſt perfectly good,</hi> (which in it ſelf is a great truth, but not that <hi>he decreed all things whatſoever come to paſs,</hi> then he decreed things that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly evil, which is contradictory) <hi>neither is there any thing of it ſelf abſolutely evil,</hi> then it muſt be abſolutely good. This is the bottom of this horrid and impious Principle of Faith, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed tends to end all Religion.</p>
            <p>And of this Faith, they would inſinuate the Reader, all ſound Chriſtians to be; but I know many more (and I hope there are moe Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Chriſtians) that do abhor it than believe it; and they had done well and honeſtly to have diſtinguiſhed, ſeeing they could not but know there are more of a contrary Faith in this matter
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66029:31"/> than themſelves, but that they would have People to believe that they are of the only true ſound Faith, whereas, if there be any Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, or Apoſtacy from the true Faith in the World, it may be found here, ſeeing none can be worſe.</p>
            <p>4. And as for a ſuppoſition of raſhneſs, and out-running the Bounds of Moderation, and a Goſpel-ſpirit in this matter, I ſay, No; and I doubt not but it will ſo appear to unbyaſſed Perſons, the depth of the matter being ſeriouſly pondered, it being not Perſons, but things I am contending againſt, even <hi>ſpiritual Wickedneſs in high places:</hi> It is for the Name of God, Chriſt and the Goſpel: it is againſt this God-diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring, Goſpel-deſtroying, Sin-exalting, and Soul-undoing Principle of Faith that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, I deſign no wrong to Men, but their eternal Good, their Repentance.</p>
            <p>But as for this horrid Principle, whoſe birth (as is moſt manifeſt) is from the Prince and Power of Darkneſs, I cannot ſpare, and that it is from Satan, and not from above, is moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
            <p>For, 1. It is not of God. What? ſhall we believe that God decreed things that are ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely contrary to his Name, Nature, and holy Word? ſhall we believe that God decreed things which himſelf calls <hi>abominable things, which he hates, and filthy ſtinking things,</hi> Jer. 44. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66029:32"/> 14. 1, 2, 3. <hi>deteſtible and abominable things,</hi> Jer. 16 18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 5. 11. and 7. 20. <hi>accurſed things, Joſh. 7. 13, 15. wicked things that provoke him to anger,</hi> 2 King. 17 11. <hi>horrible things,</hi> Jer. 18. 13. and 23. 14. yea, things that <hi>never came into the heart of God</hi> to have done, Jer. 7. 31. I ſay, ſhall we believe that God decreed all theſe things; it's a Faith to be abhorred of all ſerious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, it turning the whole Book of God into a lye.</p>
            <p>2. As it is not of God, ſo it is immoral, and never came from the Light of Nature, that hath more honourable thoughts of God, than to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the wicked acts of Men upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; we may truly ſay, as <hi>Jer. 18. 13. Ask ye now among the Heathen, who hath heard ſuch things? the Virgin of</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath done a very hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing:</hi> Therefore it muſt needs be from the Prince and Power of Darkneſs thus to belye the Lord, it being contrary to the holy Name, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Word of God, and an abhorrency to the Law and Light of Nature.</p>
            <p>And therefore I cannot ſpare this impious Principle of Abſolute Reprobation of the World by an immutable Decree before it was made, as if God had made the World for no other end but by an eternal Decree to ſin and be damned. I would ſhame yea ſet fire on this impious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, even the fire of the Word and Spirit of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66029:32"/> Truth, to the end (if poſſible) this prodigious monſter, with all its impious concomitants, might be fired and frighted out of the World, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnd to its place, and never be named among Men any more, eſpecially as an Article of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, I would if I might, give it its deaths wound, that there might be no need of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtroke, it having filled the World with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and contention for many generations; if it might now have its end, God will have the Glory, and Men the advantage.</p>
            <p>Thus, according to the advice therein, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as prudently as I could, and according to the beſt light and underſtanding that God hath given me herein, conſidered and pondered this matter, and have herein given a very brief account thereof, to the intent that it may be a word of warning to all, to beware of being corrupted thereby, and that the aſſerters thereof may ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily repent and blot it out of their Creed, and I pray the Lord to grant them Grace ſo to do. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhould be inquiſitive to know my thoughts about the eternal Decrees and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, 1. My deſire is, not to have any thoughts of God, or of his Decrees, but ſuch as are holy and honourable to his Name, which that it may ſo be,</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66029:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66029:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66029:34"/>
            <p>2. I dare not think of any Decree in God, that is contrary to his holy Name and Nature, nor in it ſelf (diſtinct from ſin as the cauſe) contrary to the good of Men, nor contrary to his holy Word, his revealed Will, and Law of Grace to Men: if I ſhould, I muſt therein make null and void all his Word, or at beſt render it uncertain, and ſo no ground or rule of Faith.</p>
            <p>3. That his revealed Will, both in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, Promiſes, and Threats, is his decreed Will, opened, revealed and made known to Men in his Word, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 20, 27.</p>
            <p>4. That all his own Works of Creation, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the Reſtitution, and World to come, with all the means tending thereunto, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by him, <hi>Act. 15. 18. Epheſ.</hi> 1. 11. but not all nor any of the Sins of Men.</p>
            <p>5. That there is, nor never was any ſecret Decree or Will in God, contrary to his revealed Word and Will made known to Men, in which our ſafety is aſſured, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
            <p>6. That it's my concern, to deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to know his revealed Will, and it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and live to him therein; aſſuring my ſelf there is no ſecret Will in God that is contrary thereunto, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 29.</p>
            <p>But I believe it to be an Abomination to be abhorred, to believe that all the actions of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66029:34"/> and Men, are the conception and birth of the eternal Decree of God. All that is good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of and from God, and all the evil acts of Sin being of and from the Devil, and Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and the evil of puniſhment from God, as the juſt and righteous reward of puniſhment, or wages of Sin.</p>
            <p>2. And as concerning Providence. 1. That God by his Providence ordereth and governeth all things well, and that Afflictions come not to paſs by chance or fortune (as Men uſually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it) but by the over-ruling hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>Job</hi> 5. 6. and that by the ſame over-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Providence, all the afflictions of his People ſhall work for their good. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 28.</p>
            <p>And that though God decreed not the ſinful acts of any, no not the <hi>Jews</hi> crucifying Chriſt, nor <hi>Judas</hi> betraying him, nor <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Brethren ſelling him to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> yet he foreſeeing they would do it, left them to the libertiy of their own wills in the matter: and by over-ruling Providence brings about his own deſignes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to his own praiſe; but that Providence hath an over-ruling hand in the Sins of Men, for accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing thereof, according to his eternal Decree, (any otherwiſe than by bare permiſſion, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling thereof as before I ſaid) I proteſt againſt, as moſt unholy to imagine.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Let the Reader, <hi>prove all things,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:66029:35"/> 
               <hi>and hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 21.</p>
            <p>Rom. 12. 9. <hi>Abhor that which is evil, and cleave to that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. 4. 8. <hi>Finally, Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <head>Theſe Books following have been lately printed for the Author, <hi>Thomas Collier.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Body of Divinity, or a Confeſſion of Faith: being the Subſtance of Chriſtianity; containing the moſt material things relating both to matters of Faith and Practice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Additional Word to the Body of Divinity; being the Subſtance of Chriſtianity, added on ſpecial occaſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Doctrine of Election, Univerſal and ſpecial Grace. Being an Eſſay for Peace and Union amongſt all the Sons and Daughters of Peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A ſober and moderate Anſwer to <hi>Nehemiah Cox</hi>'s Invective (pretended) Refutation (as he ſaith) of the groſs Errors and Hereſies aſſerted by <hi>Thomas Collier</hi> in his Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional VVord: VVherein his Refutation is examined, and found too light.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66029:35"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
